# Jaime E. FORERO-ROMERO

Born October 14, 1981. Bogotá, Colombia

http://wwwprof.uniandes.edu.co/~je.forero/http://github.com/foreroje.forero at uniandes dot edu dot coCalle 18A# 1 - 10Bloque Ip, Of. 208Universidad de los AndesAA 4976, Bogotá, Colombia

### Bio

Dr. Jaime E. Forero-Romero is a theoretical astrophysicist living in Bogotá, Colombia. Ancien élève of the École Normale Supérieure in Paris, after obtaining his PhD in 2007 he spent four years in Berlin as a postdoctoral researcher in the Cosmology group at the Leibniz-Institute for Astrophysics in Postdam. He was awarded the Gruber Fellowship in 2011 by the International Astronomical Union to spend one year in the Astronomy Department at the University of California in Berkeley. During the same period he took part in different Art & Science projects, most notably taking part in the Fluid Skies collaboration. Since mid 2012 he is an Assistant Professor in the Physics Department at Universidad de los Andes in Bogotá.

#### Education

- PhD. Physics, Ecole Normale Supérieure de Lyon (France) 11/2007
- M.Sc. Physics (Magistre Interuniversitaire) Ecole Normale Supérieure (Paris, France), 08/2005
- Undergraduate Physics studies (3 $^{rd}$ -4 $^{th}$ years), Instituto Balseiro (Argentina), 08/2001 08/2003
- Undergraduate Physics studies (1 $^{st}$ -2 $^{nd}$  years), U. Nacional de Colombia, 07/1999 07/2001

### **Academic Positions**

- Assistant Professor, Physics Department, Universidad de los Andes (Colombia), 8/2012-
- Gruber Fellow at the Astronomy Department UC Berkeley (USA), 10/2011-7/2012
- Postdoctoral Researcher at the Leibniz Institute for Astrophysics-Potsdam (AIP) (Germany), 10/2007-9/2011
- Graduate student at the Ecole Normale Supérieure de Lyon (France), 09/2006-09/2007
- Élève at the Ecole Normale Supérieure (Paris, France), 09/2003-08/2006
- Undergraduate fellow at the Instituto Balseiro (Bariloche, Argentina), 08/2001-08/2003

# Honors and Awards

- 2011. IAU Peter and Patricia Gruber Foundation Fellowship
- 2006-2007. Graduate Research Fellowship (Allocation Couplée) of the French Ministry for Research and Education.
- 2003-2006. Scholarship at the Ecole Normale Supérieure (Paris), covers tuition fees plus room and board to pursue graduate studies and PhD research.
- 2001-2003. Undergraduate scholarship (covers tuition fees at the Instituto Balseiro plus room and board) from the Argentinian Atomic Energy Comission.
- 1999. Gold Medal in the National Chemistry Olympiad, Bogotá, Colombia (First Place, National Competition)

# Teaching

- 2013-II. Computational Physics. Universidad de los Andes.
- 2013-II. Physics II (Thermodynamics and Electromagnetism). Universidad de los Andes.
- 2013-I. Computational Physics. Universidad de los Andes.

- 2013-I. Physics I (Newtonian Mechanics). Universidad de los Andes.
- 2012-II. Physics I (Newtonian Mechanics). Universidad de los Andes.
- 2012-II. Introduction to Physics (module on Astrophysics). Universidad de los Andes.
- Lectures on Galaxy Evolution, V Colombian Astrophysics Summer School, Observatorio Astronomico Nacional, Summer 2009
- Introduction to Astrophysics (Teaching Assistant), Undergraduate Level Course at the University of Lyon I, Spring 2007.

### **Publication Statistics**

- 14 Refereed journal articles in astrophysics since 2007. Total Number of Citations: 176. H-index: 8. (Source: ADS)
- 2 Manuscripts in reviewing process.

### Selected Talks

Since 2006, different seminars at Max Planck Institute for Astrophysics, University of British Columbia, Marseille Observatory, Hebrew U. of Jerusalem, U. Nacional Autónoma de México, U. de Antioquia (Colombia), Observatorio Astronómico Nacional (Colombia), U. Nacional de Colombia, U. de los Andes (Colombia), New Mexico State U., Arizona State U., Columbia U., Princeton U., Harvard U., UC Berkeley, UC Santa Cruz, Pontificia Universidad Catolica (Chile), Universidad de Chile.

#### Art & Science

- 2012: Founding member and organizer of the Art and Science Meetings (Encuentros de Arte y Ciencia) in Bogotá.
- Since 2011 member of the *Fluid Skies* collaboration together with Yunchul Kim (artist) and Lucia Ayala (Art Historian). *Fluid Skies* is a creative and research platform to explore the fluid materiality of the cosmos from the perspectives of astrophysics, art, history and philosophy.
- 2010, Talk on *Simulations of Large Scale Structure Evolution*, Institut für Raumexperimente Olafur Eliasson Studio, Berlin.

### Languages

Spanish (native), English (fluent), French (fluent), German (proficient)